Register of the Jo Ann Gasper papers, 1970-1993
Hoover Institution Archives
Jo Ann Gasper papers
1970-1993
86012
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Gasper, Jo Ann.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Jo Ann Gasper was born September 25th, 1946, in Providence, Rhode Island. She received her B.A. in Political Philosophy in 1967, and an M.B.A. in 1969, from the University of Dallas. Gasper started her professional career in 1976 as the editor and publisher of The Right Woman newsletter, whose primary focus was centered on family and women’s issues. Additionally, the newsletter provided independent consultation on public policy issues and business procedures. Due to her expertise in family and social policy, Gasper served as a Family Policy Advisor to the Reagan and Bush 1980 presidential campaign. She continued her political career at the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, where she served as the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Population Affairs. During her time as Deputy Assistant Secretary for Population Affairs she was responsible for the administration of the National Family Planning Program and the Adolescent Family Life Program. Gasper was released from her position in 1987 by the Secretary of Health and Human Services, Otis R. Bowen, for her refusal to issue grants to two Planned Parenthood groups. In 1987, Gasper joined the U.S. Department of Education in the capacity of Policy Advisor to the Under Secretary of Education, where she worked on issues related to Youth and Family Policy, specifically: adolescent pregnancy, abortion, sex education, and contraceptive services. Jo Ann Gasper retired from her political career in the 1990s.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection documents the political activities of Jo Ann Gasper from 1970 to 1993. The collection is focused on her time as the editor and publisher of The Right Woman newsletter, as the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Population Affairs for the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, and as the Policy Advisor to the Under Secretary for the U.S. Department of Education. Materials in the collection are comprised of biographical files, correspondence, printed matter, research, speeches and writings.
Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Congress.; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services.; Birth control--United States.; Conservatism.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; United States--Social policy.; Women--United States.
- Biographical File, 1970-1993
  Scope and Contents
  Comprised of articles, certificates, photographs, resume copies, interviews, and documents regarding termination of the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Population Affairs position.
  - Articles, 1977-1987 (Text 1: 1)
  - Certificates, 1985 (Text 1: 2)
  - Interviews, September 16, 1993 (Text 1: 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1970 (Text 1: 4)
  - Professional Appointments and Resumes, circa 1980 (Text 1: 5)
  - Receipts, 1988 (Text 1: 6)
  - Termination Documents, July, 1987 (Text 1: 7-8)
- Correspondence, 1977-1987
  Composed of professional and personal correspondence during time in office and prior to retirement.
  - Letters by Others, 1977-1987 (Text 1: 9)
  - Letters of Endorsement, 1986 (Text 1: 10)
  - Letters Received, 1977-1987 (Text 1: 11)
  - Letters Sent, 1977-1987 (Text 1: 12)
- Printed Matter, 1971-1981
  Comprised of pamphlets, brochures, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and conference materials.
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1971-1976 (Text 2: 1)
  - Christian Citizen, 1981 (Text 2: 2)
  - Clippings, January, 1978 - April, 1978 (Text 2: 3-6)
  - Clippings, July, 1978 - August, 1978 (Text 2: 7-8)
  - Clippings, October, 1978 - December, 1978 (Text 2: 9-11)
  - Clippings, January, 1979 - August, 1979 (Text 2: 12-19)
  - Clippings, September, 1979 - December, 1979 (Text 3: 1-4)
  - Clippings, January, 1980 - February, 1980 (Text 3: 5-6)
  - Clippings, crica 1980 (Text 3: 7)
  - Conference Materials, 1987 (Text 3: 8)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1980 (Text 3: 9)
  - The Newsletter of Newsletters, 1977-1981 (Text 4: 1)
  - The Newsletter of Newsletters (Administration), 1978-1981 (Text 4: 2)
  - The Right Woman, 1978 (Text 4: 3-6)
  - The Right Woman (Administration), 1978-1981 (Text 5: 1)
- Research, 1978-1990
  Composed of research materials gathered during time in office regarding family planning, education, pro-choice materials, abortion, pornography, domestic violence, sex education, homosexuality, religion, Family Protection Act, Title X, child welfare, social security, and IRS exemptions.
  - Adolescent Pregnancy and Childbearing, circa 1990 (Text 5: 2)
  - Copyright Exemptions for Religious Organizations, 1981 (Text 5: 3)
  - Domestic Violence, 1979-1982 (Text 5: 4)
  - Education, 1988 (Text 5: 5)
  - Family Protection Act, 1979 (Text 5: 6)
  - I.R.S. - Tax Exempt Organizations (Application Materials), 1979 (Text 5: 7)
  - I.R.S. - Tax Exempt Schools, 1978-1979 (Text 6: 1-2)
  - Population, 1978 (Text 6: 3)
  - Pornography, 1986 (Text 6: 4)
  - Presidential Documents, 1987 (Text 6: 5)
  - Right to Life Bill, 1981 (Text 6: 6)
  - School Based Clinics, 1986-1988 (Text 6: 7)
  - Sex-Education, circa 1990 (Text 7: 1)
  - Social Security, 1979-1980 (Text 7: 2)
  - Taxpayers Bill of Rights, 1981 (Text 7: 3)
  - The Pope in America, October 1-7, 1979 (Text 7: 4)
  - The Presidential Commission for the National Agenda for the Eighties, 1979-1980 (Text 7: 5)
  - Title X - Family Planning, 1985-1987 (Text 7: 6)
  - 97th Congress: Congressional Record, 1981 (Text 7: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1981-1990
  Comprised of drafts of speeches and talks, correspondence regarding speaking engagements, notes, as well as copies of authored writings.
  - Accepted Speaking Engagements, 1987 (Text 8: 1)
  - Capitol Connection, 1981 (Text 8: 2)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Text 8: 3)
  - Drafts of Speeches, 1987 (Text 8: 4)
  - Handouts, circa 1990 (Text 8: 5)
  - Notes, circa 1990 (Text 8: 6)
  - Research, 1987-1990 (Text 8: 7)
  - Writings, 1980 (Text 8: 8)